Titanic had enough
lifeboats to satisfy the
law.
That sentence sounds
safe.
In 1912, it was the
problem.
British rules measured
lifeboats by tonnage.
Above 10,000 tons, the
top bracket required
16 lifeboats for 990
people.
Titanic carried 16
lifeboats and four
collapsibles, enough
for about 1,176 people.
More than 2,200 were
aboard.
The paperwork said
compliant.
The ship said
otherwise.
Some boats left
underfilled.
The law failed one way.
Evacuation failed
another.
Afterward,
investigators pushed the
correction.
Count people carried,
not tonnage.
Two years later, Solis
turned that lesson
into international
rulemaking.
The old category kept
measuring yesterday's
ship while approving
tomorrow's risk.
Small causes, massive
consequences.