Titanic had enough lifeboats to satisfy
the law. That sentence sounds safe.
In 1912, it was the problem.
British rules measured lifeboats by
tonnage. Above 10,000 tons, the top
bracket required sixteen lifeboats for 990
people. Titanic carried sixteen lifeboats
and four collapsibles, enough for about
1,176 people. More than 2,200 were aboard.
The paperwork said compliant.
The ship said otherwise.
Some boats left underfilled.
The law failed one way;
evacuation failed another. Afterward,
investigators pushed the correction: count
people carried, not tonnage.
Two years later, SOLAS turned that lesson
into international rulemaking. The old
category kept measuring yesterday's ship
while approving tomorrow's risk.
Small causes, massive consequences.