SPEAKER_00: Titanic had enough lifeboats to satisfy the law.
SPEAKER_00: That sentence sounds safe.
SPEAKER_00: In 1912, it was the problem.
SPEAKER_00: British rules measured lifeboats by tonnage.
SPEAKER_00: Above 10,000 tons, the top bracket required 16 lifeboats for 990 people.
SPEAKER_00: Titanic carried 16 lifeboats and four collapsibles, enough for about 1,176 people.
SPEAKER_00: More than 2,200 were aboard.
SPEAKER_00: The paperwork said compliant.
SPEAKER_00: The ship said otherwise.
SPEAKER_00: Some boats left underfilled.
SPEAKER_00: The law failed one way.
SPEAKER_00: Evacuation failed another.
SPEAKER_00: Afterward, investigators pushed the correction.
SPEAKER_00: Count people carried, not tonnage.
SPEAKER_00: Two years later, Solis turned that lesson into international rulemaking.
SPEAKER_00: The old category kept measuring yesterday's ship while approving tomorrow's risk.
SPEAKER_00: Small causes, massive consequences.