At the Hyatt Regency, the deadly change
looked like a shortcut.
The walkway design used one continuous
hanger rod from roof to fourth floor
to second floor.
In shop drawings, it became two shorter
rods, easier to build.
But the load path changed.
The fourth floor connection now carried both
walkways, not one.
The load essentially doubled.
nbs later found the original design was
already weak the revision left roughly
one-third of code expected capacity on july
17 1981 two walkways collapsed during a
crowded dance official records count 113
dead and 186 injured
This was not a shop detail.
It was a structural redesign.
Every handoff treated it like paperwork.
Small causes, massive consequences.