The 737 MAX was sold as a
familiar airplane.
That was the commercial
promise.
Airlines could keep crews,
schedules, and training
close to the old 737.
Then Boeing put larger CFM
Leap engines
on the aircraft.
They sat farther forward
and higher on
the wing, and under
certain high angle
of attack conditions, the
jet could pitch
up differently.
MCAS was built to make
that new
behavior feel familiar,
but the system could
move the stabilizer from
one angle of
attack sensor.
Pilots were not clearly
trained that it
existed by name.
After Lionair 610, the
warning still was
not reclassified fast
enough as an architectural
problem.
The plane had changed.
The story told to the
people flying
it had not.
Small causes, massive
consequences.