By January 1986, the
Space Shuttle had
flown twenty-four
times.
Each flight
reinforced one idea —
the system worked.
Across those
flights, engineers
documented O-ring
damage.
Erosion, blow-by —
hot gas past seals
designed to hold.
Low-temperature
flights all showed
distress.
But each flight
survived, and the
warning lost force.
Danger became a
known condition.
A stop signal became
a line item.
The night before
Challenger, engineers
recommended against
launch.
The burden shifted —
instead of proving
it safe to fly,
they were asked to
prove it was
unsafe.
On the coldest
morning the program had
ever faced,
seventy-three seconds was
all the physics
needed.
The warning was
never missing.
It had been made
survivable for too
long.
Small causes,
massive consequences.