SPEAKER_00: The 737 MAX was sold as a familiar airplane.
SPEAKER_00: That was the commercial promise.
SPEAKER_00: Airlines could keep crews, schedules, and training close to the old 737.
SPEAKER_00: Then Boeing put larger CFM Leap engines on the aircraft.
SPEAKER_00: They sat farther forward and higher on the wing, and under certain high angle of attack conditions, the jet could pitch up differently.
SPEAKER_00: MCAS was built to make that new behavior feel familiar, but the system could move the stabilizer from one angle of attack sensor.
SPEAKER_00: Pilots were not clearly trained that it existed by name.
SPEAKER_00: After Lionair 610, the warning still was not reclassified fast enough as an architectural problem.
SPEAKER_00: The plane had changed.
SPEAKER_00: The story told to the people flying it had not.
SPEAKER_00: Small causes, massive consequences.