By January 1986, the space
shuttle had
flown 24 times.
Each flight reinforced one
idea.
The system worked.
Across those flights,
engineers documented O-ring
damage.
Erosion, blow-by, hot gas
pass seals designed
to hold.
Low-temperature flights
all showed distress.
But each flight survived,
and the warning
lost force.
Danger became a known
condition.
A stop signal became a
line item.
The night before
Challenger, engineers recommended
against launch.
The burden shifted.
Instead of proving it safe
to fly,
they were asked to prove
it was
unsafe.
On the coldest morning the
program had
ever faced, 73 seconds was
all the
physics needed.
The warning was never
missing.
It had been made
survivable for too
long.
Small causes, massive
consequences.