In 1940, the Tacoma Narrows Bridge looked
like the future.
It was long, slender, cheaper than the
original conservative design, and beautiful
enough to make its movement famous.
People called it Galloping Gertie.
the wind on collapse day was not
extraordinary the bridge had already survived
stronger autumn winds the hidden problem was
what the bridge did to the air
after it started moving its shallow solid
plate girder deck was too flexible in
torsion
Once the roadway began to twist, the
motion changed the airflow, and the changed
airflow fed the next twist.
Engineers were studying the motion, but the
design culture had not yet made dynamic
aerodynamic testing routine for bridges like
this.
The bridge did not just meet wind.
It entered a behavior its own design
made possible.
Small causes.
Massive consequences.