SPEAKER_00: At the Hyatt Regency, the deadly change looked like a shortcut.
SPEAKER_00: The walkway design used one continuous hanger rod from roof to fourth floor to second floor.
SPEAKER_00: In shop drawings, it became two shorter rods, easier to build.
SPEAKER_00: But the load path changed.
SPEAKER_00: The fourth floor connection now carried both walkways, not one.
SPEAKER_00: The load essentially doubled.
SPEAKER_00: nbs later found the original design was already weak the revision left roughly one-third of code expected capacity on july 17 1981 two walkways collapsed during a crowded dance official records count 113 dead and 186 injured
SPEAKER_00: This was not a shop detail.
SPEAKER_00: It was a structural redesign.
SPEAKER_00: Every handoff treated it like paperwork.
SPEAKER_00: Small causes, massive consequences.