SPEAKER_00: In Vienna, two maternity wards sat under one hospital roof.
SPEAKER_00: The first clinic was run by doctors and students.
SPEAKER_00: The second was run by midwives.
SPEAKER_00: The patients were similar.
SPEAKER_00: The death rates were not.
SPEAKER_00: By 1846, the first clinic was losing more than one in ten mothers.
SPEAKER_00: Across the same years, the second stayed under 4%.
SPEAKER_00: Semmelweis found the difference in the routine.
SPEAKER_00: Doctors moved from autopsies to childbirth without effective disinfection.
SPEAKER_00: He required chloride of lime hand disinfection.
SPEAKER_00: Mortality fell.
SPEAKER_00: The evidence worked before germ theory could explain why.
SPEAKER_00: That was the problem.
SPEAKER_00: Believing the data meant believing doctors had been carrying death from the dead to the living.
SPEAKER_00: The institution protected its identity longer than it protected the evidence.
SPEAKER_00: Small causes, massive consequences.