SPEAKER_00: In 1940, the Tacoma Narrows Bridge looked like the future.
SPEAKER_00: It was long, slender, cheaper than the original conservative design, and beautiful enough to make its movement famous.
SPEAKER_00: People called it Galloping Gertie.
SPEAKER_00: But the wind on collapse day was not extraordinary.
SPEAKER_00: The bridge had already survived stronger autumn winds.
SPEAKER_00: The hidden problem was what the bridge did to the air after it started moving.
SPEAKER_00: Its shallow solid plate girder deck was too flexible in torsion.
SPEAKER_00: Once the roadway began to twist, the motion changed the airflow, and the changed airflow fed the next twist.
SPEAKER_00: Engineers were studying the motion, but the design culture had not yet made dynamic aerodynamic testing routine for bridges like this.
SPEAKER_00: The bridge did not just meet wind.
SPEAKER_00: It entered a behavior its own design made possible.
SPEAKER_00: Small causes, massive consequences.