In Vienna, two maternity wards sat under
one hospital roof. The First Clinic was
run by doctors and students.
The Second was run by midwives.
The patients were similar.
The death rates were not.
By 1846, the First Clinic was losing
more than one in ten mothers.
Across the same years, the Second stayed
under four percent. Semmelweis found the
difference in the routine.
Doctors moved from autopsies to childbirth
without effective disinfection. He
required chloride-of-lime hand
disinfection. Mortality fell. The evidence
worked before germ theory could explain
why. That was the problem.
Believing the data meant believing doctors
had been carrying death from the dead
to the living. The institution protected
its identity longer than it protected the
evidence. Small causes, massive
consequences.