On November 7, 1940, the Tacoma Narrows Bridge
collapsed into Puget Sound.
It had opened on July 1.
Four months later, it was gone.
The wind that morning was not extraordinary.
It was measured at 38 miles per hour
at 7:30 a.m. and about 42 miles per
hour near the bridge's east end two hours
later. The bridge had already ridden through earlier
autumn storms with winds over 50 miles per
hour. What it could not survive was the
way its own motion changed the air around
it, and what that air then did back
to the bridge. For a little over an
hour before the collapse, the bridge twisted.
Not simply swayed, and not only bounced.
The roadway rotated along its length,
one side rising as the other fell,
in a motion that grew steadily larger.
Leonard Coatsworth, whose car had been thrown against
the curb, climbed out and crawled toward the
East Tower as the deck rolled beneath him.
Engineers and photographers were watching.
Motion-picture footage survives. The bridge did not
fail because November 7 brought some unprecedented
gale. It failed because the bridge and the
wind entered a feedback cycle the design had
never been tested against.
Once that cycle took hold,
each oscillation helped feed the next.
This episode is not about a freak storm
or a cartoon version of bad engineering.
It is about what happens when a structure
is optimized for the forces engineers know how
to calculate, while a different class of forces
remains outside the design process.
The original proposal for a bridge across the
Narrows came from Clark Eldridge,
lead engineer for the Washington State Highway
Department. His design was conservative by the
standards of the day: a two-lane suspension bridge
with deep, open stiffening trusses,
twenty-five feet deep, along the deck.
That design was not the one that got
built. When Washington sought federal funding,
the Public Works Administration required outside
consultants. Leon Moisseiff, one of the most prominent
suspension bridge engineers in the United States,
redesigned the superstructure. He had helped shape the
theory behind some of the country's great suspension
bridges. He was respected and accomplished.
He also told the PWA his revisions would
cut the estimated cost from roughly eleven million
dollars to seven. The critical change was the
deck. Instead of Eldridge's deep open trusses,
Moisseiff used solid plate girders just eight feet
deep. Where Eldridge's deck would have let much
more air pass through, Moisseiff's presented a broader
solid surface to the wind.
The bridge was also extraordinarily slender.
Its center span was 2,800 feet long,
while the deck was only 39 feet wide
between the cables, a ratio of one to
seventy-two. For bridge designers of the 1930s,
that kind of lightness and grace looked like
the future. The redesign was approved.
Construction began in November 1938.
The bridge opened to traffic on July 1,
1940. Almost immediately, it moved.
Drivers and pedestrians noticed the vertical
undulation first. The deck rose and fell in
long waves. The motion was so conspicuous that
the bridge quickly acquired a nickname:
Galloping Gertie. Engineers knew about the movement.
Before the collapse, the state had already hired
University of Washington engineer F.
B. Farquharson to study the oscillations and recommend
remedies. Tie-down cables had been installed on the
side spans. Wind deflectors were under active
consideration. The movement was not treated as an
immediate emergency. It was treated as an alarming
peculiarity, but still a manageable one.
People drove across the bridge for the experience.
Each day the bridge moved and remained standing
made the motion easier to categorize as a
property of the bridge rather than evidence of
a failure already in progress.
That matters. Visible anomaly had been normalized
before the catastrophic mode ever arrived.
On the morning of November 7,
the bridge's behavior changed.
The familiar vertical motion gave way to torsional
motion. Shortly after 10:00 a.m.,
the deck began twisting.
By 11:10 a.m., the center span had fallen.
What followed was not the wind simply overpowering
the structure. It was a flexible structure interacting
with wind in a way the design framework
of the time did not know how to
evaluate well. To understand why,
you have to look at five conditions that
were in place before the first cable was
spun. First: the redesign prioritized slenderness,
economy, and visual grace.
Moisseiff's work grew out of deflection theory,
an advanced framework for suspension bridges.
In that framework, the dead weight of the
bridge, the cable system, and the stiffness already
built into the structure could do far more
of the stabilizing work than older practice had
assumed. The payoff was real.
Bridges could be longer, lighter,
cheaper, and in the eyes of many engineers,
more beautiful. For the loads that theory modeled
well, it was powerful.
Tacoma Narrows was not built by ignoring engineering.
It was built by applying advanced engineering within
the limits of what that engineering had formalized.
Second: bridge design theory still treated wind mainly
as a static load, not a dynamic conversation
between air and structure.
In the 1930s, suspension bridge engineers were highly
capable at analyzing gravity loads,
traffic loads, and steady horizontal wind pressure.
What they did not yet have was a
mature, standardized framework for aerodynamic
behavior in very flexible long-span bridges.
Wind was generally treated as a force that
pushed on the structure, not as something that
changed when the structure itself began to move.
That distinction is everything.
If a bridge moves in wind,
it changes the airflow around its deck.
The changed airflow alters the force on the
deck. That altered force changes the next motion.
The bridge is no longer just resisting wind.
It is helping create the conditions of its
own next displacement. Dynamic wind-tunnel testing
existed in aeronautics. It was not yet a
routine requirement in suspension-bridge design.
Third: the bridge's motion had already been absorbed
into the category of spectacle.
Between July and November 1940,
the bridge's oscillations were visible,
documented, and widely discussed.
Farquharson was studying them.
Remedies were being developed.
But traffic continued, the nickname stuck,
and the bridge's motion became part of its
identity in public life.
When a system produces conspicuous abnormal behavior
and survives, people begin to discount the warning.
The bridge taught its observers that movement could
be dramatic without being fatal.
That lesson held until it didn't.
Fourth: the design had not been subjected to
the kind of aerodynamic testing that later became
standard. This was the clearest gap.
The problem was not that the calculations were
sloppy. The problem was that the design process
of 1940 did not yet routinely demand a
dynamic aerodynamic investigation of a bridge deck
like this one. After the collapse,
the federal investigating board identified excessive
flexibility, the aerodynamic effect of the solid
plate-girder deck, and the need for wind-tunnel model
testing as central lessons.
Those lessons were learned after the bridge fell,
not before it was built.
Fifth: once the bridge entered large torsional motion,
the motion itself began feeding the forces acting
on it. Engineers still debate some details of
the transition from vertical oscillation to
catastrophic twisting. But the standard modern
explanation centers on self-excited torsional flutter,
a self-reinforcing twisting instability.
In that kind of instability,
the twisting of the deck changes the airflow
in a way that adds energy back into
the twist. The motion becomes self-reinforcing.
The wind did not need to become a
hurricane. It only needed to keep supplying the
flow field that the moving bridge was already
turning into fuel. This is why Tacoma Narrows
is so often misunderstood.
The famous footage tempts people to call it
a simple resonance story, as if the wind
just happened to hit one magic frequency and
the bridge obediently shook itself apart.
That is too simple.
The stronger account is an aerodynamic one:
vertical motion, vortex effects, torsional
instability, and a bridge deck so flexible that
once the twisting mode took hold,
the airflow and the structure began driving each
other. The bridge did not merely fail in
the wind. It became aerodynamically unstable in the
wind. The collapse had an immediate effect on
the profession, even if the exact mechanism was
not settled in a single afternoon.
Investigations began at once.
The federal board reported in March 1941.
University of Washington wind-tunnel work continued
through the 1940s. The Advisory Board on the
Investigation of Suspension Bridges met from 1942 to
1954. Engineers re-evaluated other long-span
suspension bridges and began designing later spans
with far greater attention to aerodynamic stability.
The replacement Tacoma Narrows Bridge,
opened in 1950, looked much more like Eldridge's
original instinct than Moisseiff's 1940 deck.
It used a much deeper open stiffening truss,
features to let air pass through the deck,
and additional damping devices.
That was not an aesthetic correction.
It was a new engineering answer to a
newly formalized problem. The collapse did not reveal
engineering negligence in the simple moralized sense.
Moisseiff was not guessing.
He was applying the best accepted theory available
to him, and that theory had worked impressively
within its domain. What the collapse revealed was
that the domain itself had an edge.
Past that edge, the equations were not wrong.
They were incomplete. The deeper failure was not
that the bridge was slender,
or beautiful, or inexpensive.
It was that the design tools used to
judge the bridge were optimized for loads they
had been built to handle,
while aerodynamic instability in flexible bridge decks
had not yet been fully absorbed into ordinary
bridge practice. The bridge was not dynamically vetted
against that problem in the way later generations
would consider essential. This kind of failure recurs
across the history of engineering.
It is not the failure of knowingly ignoring
a risk. It is the failure of working
inside a framework that has not yet formalized
a real risk, even when clues to that
risk are already present.
In aviation, aerodynamic behavior was already central.
In suspension-bridge design, it had not yet crossed
fully into routine design practice.
The knowledge was nearby.
The discipline boundary was real.
After November 7, 1940, that boundary did not
survive intact. The field changed because it had
to. Wind-tunnel testing became commonplace.
Aerodynamic stability became a standard concern in
long-span bridge design. Designers paid much closer
attention to deck shape, torsional stiffness,
damping, and the way moving structures feed energy
back into the air around them.
That is how engineering learns.
Not cleanly. Not abstractly.
Often by discovering, in the wreckage of a
real structure, the exact point where a trusted
model stopped matching the world.
The Tacoma Narrows Bridge twisted for a little
over an hour before it fell.
Cameras were running. Engineers were watching.
By then, the bridge was already doing something
its designers had never been required to prove
it could survive. Everything needed for the failure
was present long before November 7:
the shallow plate-girder deck, the extraordinary
slenderness, the weak torsional resistance,
the absence of dynamic aerodynamic testing,
and a profession that had not yet made
those questions routine. The wind that morning did
not create the design weakness.
It revealed it. What failed at Tacoma Narrows
was a bridge. What else failed was the
boundary of a model.
The failure was real.
The cause chain was longer.
Next time: another design failure.
Another system that taught itself to ignore what
it had not yet learned how to name.