At the Hyatt Regency, the
deadly change
looked like a shortcut.
The walkway design used
one continuous hangar
rod from roof to fourth
floor to
second floor.
In shop drawings, it
became two shorter
rods, easier to build.
But the load path changed.
The fourth floor
connection now carried both
walkways, not one.
The load essentially
doubled.
NBS later found the
original design was
already weak.
The revision left roughly
one-third of code-expected
capacity.
On July 17, 1981, two
walkways collapsed
during a crowded dance.
Official records count 113
dead and 186
injured.
This was not a shop
detail.
It was a structural
redesign.
Every handoff treated it
like paperwork.
Small causes, massive
consequences.