A radiation machine gave one patient roughly
100 times the intended dose.
The manufacturer said it was impossible.
Then it happened again.
The Therac-25 replaced physical safety interlocks
with software checks.
During fast data entry, a race condition
could leave the machine in the wrong
state and fire a full power beam
with no filter.
Nobody caught it because the code had
been reused from older machines, and reused
code felt like tested code.
Operators reported errors.
The manufacturer insisted the machine was safe.
More patients were burned before the pattern
was treated as real.
The disaster was not just bad code.
It was a system with no independent
safety layer, no quick way to believe
field reports, and no design for software
being wrong.
That is how small causes become massive
consequences.