In Vienna, two maternity
wards sat under
one hospital roof.
The first clinic was run
by doctors
and students.
The second was run by
midwives.
The patients were similar.
The death rates were not.
By 1846, the first clinic
was losing
more than one in ten
mothers.
Across the same years, the
second stayed
under 4%.
Semmelweis found the
difference in the routine.
Doctors moved from
autopsies to childbirth without
effective disinfection.
He required chloride of
lime hand disinfection.
Mortality fell.
The evidence worked before
germ theory could
explain why.
That was the problem.
Believing the data meant
believing doctors had
been carrying death from
the dead to
the living.
The institution protected
its identity longer than
it protected the evidence.
Small causes, massive
consequences.