A radiation machine gave one patient
roughly a hundred times the intended dose.
The manufacturer said it was impossible.
Then it happened again.
The Therac twenty-five replaced physical
safety interlocks with software checks.
During fast data entry, a race condition
could leave the machine in the wrong
state and fire a full-power beam with
no filter.
Nobody caught it because the
code had been reused from older machines,
and reused code felt like tested code.
Operators reported errors.
The
manufacturer insisted the machine was
safe.
More patients were burned before the
pattern was treated as real.
The disaster was not just bad code.
It was a system with no independent
safety layer, no quick way to believe
field reports, and no design for software
being wrong.
That is how small causes
become massive consequences.