Titanic had enough lifeboats to satisfy the
law.
That sentence sounds safe.
In 1912, it was the problem.
British rules measured lifeboats by tonnage.
Above 10,000 tons, the top bracket required
16 lifeboats for 990 people.
Titanic carried 16 lifeboats and four collapsibles,
enough for about 1,176 people.
More than 2,200 were aboard.
The paperwork said compliant.
The ship said otherwise.
Some boats left underfilled.
The law failed one way.
Evacuation failed another.
Afterward, investigators pushed the correction.
Count people carried, not tonnage.
Two years later, SOLAS turned that lesson
into international rulemaking.
The old category kept measuring yesterday's ship
while approving tomorrow's risk.
Small causes, massive consequences.