In October 2018, Lion Air Flight 610 departed
Jakarta and crashed into the Java Sea thirteen
minutes after takeoff. All 189 people on board
were killed. Five months later,
in March 2019, Ethiopian Airlines Flight 302 departed
Addis Ababa and crashed six minutes after takeoff.
All 157 people on board were killed.
Both aircraft were Boeing 737 MAX 8s.
Both crews had fought the same automated system.
Both had lost. In the months that followed,
investigators, regulators, and a congressional
committee examined how two brand-new aircraft from the
world's most experienced commercial aviation
manufacturer had been delivered to airlines with a
flight control system that could overpower the pilots,
that depended on a single sensor for its
inputs, and that had not been fully described
in the flight manuals the pilots were trained
on. This episode is not about one faulty
sensor. It is about what happens when a
company tries to preserve the appearance of the
old system while redesigning around a new physical
reality and resolves the contradiction in software the
pilot cannot clearly see.
The Boeing 737 first flew in 1967.
Over the following five decades it became the
world's bestselling jetliner, accumulated an enormous
global maintenance and training infrastructure,
and underwent continuous revision and modernization
while retaining enough commonality across variants
that pilots could transition between versions with
limited additional training. That commonality was not
incidental. It was commercially valuable.
Airlines operating mixed fleets of 737 variants could
schedule pilots across aircraft types,
reduce training costs, and avoid the expense of
full type rating transitions.
The 737's longevity was inseparable from its
reputation for consistency. In December 2010,
Boeing's primary competitor launched the A320neo
program, featuring more fuel-efficient engines.
The announcement was a significant competitive event.
Airlines responded with interest.
Boeing faced a choice: develop an entirely new
aircraft, which would take years and cost billions,
or modernize the 737 again.
Boeing chose to modernize.
The result was the 737 MAX.
The MAX used a new engine the CFM
LEAP that was larger and more fuel-efficient than
its predecessor. The engine's size required it to
be mounted differently on the wing:
further forward and higher up than on earlier
737 variants. That repositioning changed the
aircraft's aerodynamic behavior at high angles of
attack. Specifically, under certain conditions,
the new engine placement caused the nose to
pitch up more than it had on previous
variants. This was a handling difference that could,
in principle, require pilots to learn new procedures
or require a new type rating.
Either outcome would erode the commonality argument.
The training cost advantage one of the central
commercial justifications for the MAX program depended
on the MAX flying like a 737.
So Boeing designed a software system to make
it fly like one.
The Maneuvering Characteristics Augmentation System
MCAS was introduced to compensate for the MAX's
changed pitch behavior at high angles of attack.
When the system detected conditions that could lead
to a nose-high attitude, it automatically pushed the
nose down by trimming the horizontal stabilizer.
In its original design, MCAS was a relatively
limited system. It operated in a narrow flight
envelope, moved the stabilizer a modest amount,
and was not considered significant enough to require
prominent disclosure in the flight crew operations
manual. The FAA's certification process,
which delegated substantial technical review authority
to Boeing's own engineers, did not flag it
as a major new system requiring special pilot
awareness. Then the design changed.
As flight testing proceeded, the parameters of MCAS
were expanded. The system was authorized to move
the stabilizer more up to 2.5 degrees per
activation, compared to the original 0.6 degrees.
It was authorized to activate repeatedly if the
triggering conditions persisted. And it continued to
rely on input from a single angle-of-attack sensor.
A single sensor. On an aircraft where the
system that read that sensor could push the
nose toward the ground with enough authority to
overpower a crew that did not know what
was happening, or was not clearly prepared for
the precise sequence of actions needed to stop
it. When the 737 MAX entered service,
pilots were not told MCAS existed by name.
The system was not described in the standard
flight crew operations manual.
The training materials that accompanied the MAX's
entry into service were designed around the
commonality argument the MAX was presented as a
familiar aircraft with improved engines,
not as an aircraft with a new automated
flight control system that behaved in ways previous
737s had not. The rationale was coherent within
its own logic. MCAS was designed to make
the MAX handle like a 737.
If it worked as intended,
pilots would never know it was there.
Describing a transparent background system in detail
would raise questions about why it was needed,
which would raise questions about how different the
MAX actually was, which would undermine the
commonality argument that justified the limited
training program. The system was hidden from pilots
not through malice, but because its visibility would
have cost too much.
On October 29, 2018, the crew of Lion
Air 610 encountered repeated uncommanded nose-down
inputs beginning shortly after takeoff.
The aircraft's angle-of-attack sensor the left one,
which fed MCAS had been providing erroneous readings
since a previous flight.
The crew fought the inputs.
The aircraft pitched down.
It entered the Java Sea at high speed.
The flight data recorder from Lion Air 610
showed clearly what had happened.
Boeing and the FAA were informed.
An emergency airworthiness directive was issued.
It described a runaway stabilizer condition and
directed pilots to follow existing procedures for
handling it. It did not name MCAS.
Ethiopian Airlines Flight 302 departed Addis Ababa on
March 10, 2019, four months after Lion Air
610. The crew encountered the same system,
the same failure mode, the same inputs.
They had been issued the directive.
They attempted the runaway-stabilizer response
described after Lion Air.
It was not sufficient to save the aircraft.
157 people died. The 737 MAX was grounded
worldwide two days later.
To understand how this happened,
you have to trace five conditions that were
present long before either aircraft took off.
The first: a competitive business pressure became a
design requirement. The decision to match the
A320neo's timeline by extending the 737 rather than
developing a new aircraft placed a specific constraint
on the MAX program: the result had to
be certifiable as a variant of an existing
type, with training differences that airlines could
manage within their existing 737 programs.
That constraint was not an engineering requirement.
It was a commercial one.
But it shaped every subsequent engineering decision,
because any outcome that threatened the commonality
argument threatened the program's competitive
rationale. The second: MCAS grew in authority during
development. The system that entered service was not
the system originally designed.
The expansion of MCAS's authority more stabilizer
movement, repeated activations, the same single-sensor
input was driven by flight test results that
required more compensation than the original design
had provided. Each expansion was reviewed and accepted
within the program. None triggered a reassessment of
whether the system had become something qualitatively
different from what had originally been certified.
A system that started as a background trim
function had become, by the time it reached
service, a powerful automated input capable of forcing
the aircraft into a dive.
The process that evaluated it was calibrated to
the system's origin, not its final state.
The third: single-sensor dependency was accepted as
sufficient. MCAS relied on one angle-of-attack sensor.
A single point of failure in a system
with the authority to override pilot inputs.
The rationale, as documented in the subsequent
investigations, was that MCAS was intended as a
supplement to existing protections that other systems
and procedures would catch a sensor failure before
MCAS became dangerous. That assumption required pilots
to recognize a failure mode that had not
been described to them, in an aircraft they
had been told was like the one they
already knew, under high workload conditions,
in the seconds after takeoff.
The fourth: pilot knowledge and training were limited
to preserve aircraft commonality.
The decision not to name or describe MCAS
in standard training materials was a product of
the same logic that drove the program from
the beginning. Disclosing the system meant explaining
why it existed. Explaining why it existed meant
acknowledging that the MAX handled differently from
previous 737s under certain conditions.
Acknowledging that meant undermining the commonality
claim. The training omission was not the result
of someone deciding that pilot knowledge was
unimportant. It was the result of a system
in which the commercial argument and the safety
argument were never clearly separated and in which
the commercial argument had structural priority.
The fifth: after the first crash,
the system was defended as procedure before it
was admitted as architecture.
The response to Lion Air 610 was framed
around pilot training and procedure:
the existing runaway stabilizer procedure covered the
scenario, pilots needed to know to apply it,
the airworthiness directive would address the gap.
That framing was technically defensible.
The procedure did exist.
It was theoretically applicable.
What the framing avoided was the architectural
question: whether a system with MCAS's authority,
fed by a single sensor,
undisclosed to pilots, represented a design that
should require a different response than a procedural
reminder. Ethiopian Airlines 302 answered that
question. The congressional investigation that
followed produced some of the most direct
documentation of the failure mode.
Internal Boeing communications showed employees
expressing concern about MCAS, about pressure to limit
simulator training, about the distance between what
pilots knew and what the aircraft could do.
One message, from 2017, described the aircraft as
designed by clowns supervised by monkeys.
It was written by a Boeing employee.
It was not shared with the FAA during
certification. The investigations found systemic
failures at Boeing and at the FAA's oversight
structure. The delegation of certification authority
to Boeing's own engineers, which had been standard
practice for decades, had not been matched with
sufficient independent review of systems whose scope
and authority had changed during development.
The 737 MAX returned to service in November
2020, after extensive redesign of MCAS,
new pilot training requirements that explicitly named
and described the system, and revised sensor
architecture requiring inputs from both
angle-of-attack sensors before MCAS could activate.
The aircraft that returned to service was meaningfully
different from the one that had been certified.
Which meant the one that had been certified
had been meaningfully different from what pilots had
been told it was.
The standard telling of the 737 MAX story
reaches for individual villains executives who
prioritized profit, engineers who stayed quiet,
regulators who looked away.
Those individuals exist in the record,
and their choices matter.
But the mechanism that produced two crashes was
not a conspiracy. It was a system.
A commercial constraint became a design requirement.
A design requirement shaped what could be disclosed.
What could be disclosed shaped what pilots knew.
What pilots knew determined what they could do
when the system activated.
And the system that activated had grown,
incrementally, into something that the process
evaluating it had not been recalibrated to assess.
Each step was taken inside a normal process
by people who had reviewed the step before
it. No single decision looks,
in isolation, like the choice to put 346
people at fatal risk.
The chain only becomes visible when you look
at all of it.
That is always how these chains work.
That is why they are so hard to
stop. The 737 MAX was certified as a
familiar aircraft. It was sold as a familiar
aircraft. It was trained as a familiar aircraft.
The pilots who flew it in its first
year of service had been told,
implicitly and explicitly, that what they already knew
would be sufficient. It was not sufficient.
What failed was not the sensor,
though the sensor failed.
What failed was the architecture of a system
in which a competitive argument had been allowed
to function as a safety argument in which
the demonstration that training costs could be kept
low had been allowed to stand in for
the demonstration that pilots had been given what
they needed. The system pushed the nose down.
The pilots fought it.
They had not been given a full,
explicit account of the failure mode they were
fighting. They had been told there was little
new to know. The failure was real.
The cause chain was longer.
Next time: another design failure.
Another system that taught itself to ignore what
it already knew.