In 1940, the Tacoma Narrows Bridge looked
like the future.
It was long,
slender, cheaper than the original
conservative design, and beautiful enough
to make its movement famous.
People called it Galloping Gertie.
But the wind on collapse day was
not extraordinary.
The bridge had already
survived stronger autumn winds.
The hidden problem was what the bridge
did to the air after it started
moving.
Its shallow solid plate-girder
deck was too flexible in torsion.
Once the roadway began to twist,
the motion changed the airflow,
and the changed airflow fed the next
twist.
Engineers were studying the motion,
but the design culture had not yet
made dynamic aerodynamic testing routine
for bridges like this.
The bridge did not just meet wind.
It entered a behavior its own design
made possible.
Small causes, massive
consequences.